

#### Wireless System PhD Candidate · Embedded Software Engineei

209 N 9th Street, Apt. 3B, Philadelphia, PA 19107, USA

□ (+1) 408-772-0602 | ■ danh@dnguyen.io | 🕏 www.dnguyen.io | 🖸 dnguyen85 | 🛅 dnguyen85

# Summary.

Final-year PhD candidate with 7 years' experience in research and development of hardware, software, and system components for modern wireless communication and networking systems. Fluent in embedded / FPGA development, C, Python, Matlab, and web frameworks (HTML, CSS, JS). Currently seeking full-time opportunities in the general areas of mobile computing and networking.

# **Education**

**Drexel University**Philadelphia, PA

Ph.D. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING (ADVISORS: K. R. DANDEKAR, N. KANDASAMY)

2009-Exp. 4/2017

Thesis: "Agile Spectrum Sharing Wireless Systems using Software Radios and Reconfigurable Antennas"

**Drexel University**Philadelphia, PA

M.S. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2009-2014

Hands-on experience in **computer architecture**, **hardware/software co-design**, and **telecommunications** 

**Drexel University**Philadelphia, PA

B.S. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2006–2009

Graduated Summa Cum Laude, GPA: 3.96

## Skills

**Operating Systems** Unix / Linux (proficient), Windows, MAC OS

Programming C / Python / Matlab (proficient), Java / C++ / C# (intermediate), PHP, HTML / CSS, Javascript
Libraries NumPy / Jupyter / Matplotlib / Pandas / Nikola (Python), GNU Radio (C++), lwIP / mac80211 (C)
Hardware Xilinx & Altera FPGA platforms (proficient), VHDL, Verilog, Xilinx System Generator, Modelsim

**Version Control** Git (proficient), Mercurial, SVN

**Web Framework** Node.JS with Express & MongoDB, Parse Server (mobile backend), Python Flask with MySQL, Drupal CMS

Wireless Standards IEEE 802.11a/g/n, 802.11ac, 802.11ad, LTE-A, LTE Direct, WiMAX, MIMO, mmWave

Other Skills Vim, Tmux, Terminal Shell (Bash / Zsh), Latex, Markdown, Pandoc, Microsoft Office, Inkscape, GIMP

# **Experience**

## **Drexel Wireless System Laboratory**

Philadelphia, PA

**GRADUATE RESEARCH FELLOW** 

9/2009-Present

- Led the development of a **mobile augmented reality framework** based on Unity game engine & Vuforia (frontend), with Parse & Python middleware (backend), to visualize and control RF transmissions in wireless networks in real time. See [C2,5,7] for publications. Demo video: http://beamviewer.io
- Designed and implemented a **synchronous directional wireless architecture** that leverages time synchronization and dynamic antenna directionality to perform autonomous, machine learning-based beamsteering for optimizing network throughput. Built a real-time system prototype on the WARP software-defined radio platform. Four publications [C3,4,7; W1] and a patent [P3]
- Developed an **FPGA-based software-defined radio testbed** for dynamic spectrum access research in wireless small cells, leveraging a frequency-agile frontend for flexible spectrum access. One publication [C8]
- Implemented a **real-time**, **protocol-aware reactive jammer** using GNU Radio and the low-cost USRP N210 software radio platform. Three publications [C9,10,12] and a patent [P1]
- Co-developed a **reconfigurable baseband hardware IP** for scalable ultra wide-band OFDM processing. Implemented VHDL RTL modules to interface the baseband pipeline with high-speed (1GSPS) ADC and DAC frontends. Verified hardware designs using Modelsim and Xilinx Chipscope. Two publications [C11,13]
- · Gained working knowledge of modern wireless communication systems: OFDM, CDMA, LTE, and WiMAX
- Developed and maintained the lab website at http://wireless.ece.drexel.edu

### **InterDigital Communications, Inc.**

King of Prussia, PA 6/2013–6/2014

RESEARCH INTERN - VIDEO OVER WIRELESS

- Optimized video streaming over WiFi networks leveraging IEEE 802.11e QoS support for traffic access categories
- Implemented a control algorithm for network-assisted rebuffering prevention through QoS elevation of distressed video streams
- Prototyped the experimental WiFi video delivery system using OpenWRT (on commercial routers) with modified Linux 802.11 drivers (mac80211 and n180211 modules), and DASH video clients

### **Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Drexel University**

Philadelphia, PA

**TEACHING ASSISTANT** 

2009-2014

• Taught lectures and lab sessions on Matlab, digital logic design, Java programming, and embedded systems

### **Freedom Rings Partnership**

Philadelphia, PA

WEB DEVELOPER

8/2012-8/2013

• Developed in Drupal CMS features for the Freedom Rings Partnership's KEYSPOT website (https://www.phillykeyspots.org). Responsible for static pages, news and blog posting workflow, training materials repository and search functionality, E-Learning portal, and KEYSPOT finder

MediaTech, Inc. (Vietnam)

Hanoi, Vietnam

**TECHNICAL CONSULTANT** 

1-5/2012

- Designed and implemented a proof-of-concept PBX phone system for live-broadcast TV interactive games based on Asterisk
- Performed system latency tests using landline, cellular, and SIP-based soft phones

## **Drexel High Performance Computing Laboratory**

Philadelphia, PA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (ADVISOR: J. JOHNSON)

6-12/2009

- Investigated performance bottlenecks of static auto-tuning software (ATLAS and OSKI) in sparse matrix-vector multiplication
- Analyzed and tested a lab-built Multiply-Accumulate (MAC) hardware design on FPGA using Xilinx ISE Suite

## Motorola Inc. - Home & Network Mobility Division (now ARRIS Group, Inc.)

Horsham, PA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER CO-OP

3/2008-6/2009

- Developed C++ features for the thin client software layer of set-top boxes to enhance digital video recording (DVR). Debugged and improved device drivers for external mass storage devices (eMSD) to handle DVR's external hard drive configuration process
- Implemented the System Test Program (STP) framework for automation of all design validation tests in the group

SAP America, Inc.

Newtown Square, PA

R/3 System Administrator Co-op

3-9/2007

• Provided R/3 basis technical support for SAP systems used for demo, training, and consulting purposes

# **Publications**

### **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

[C1] Enhancing Blind Interference Alignment with Reinforcement Learning

S. Begashaw, **D. H. Nguyen**, K. R. Dandekar

Proc. of IEEE Global Communications Conf. (GLOBECOM '16 - to appear), 2016

- [C2] Demo: WiART Visualize and Interact with Wireless Networks using Augmented Reality
  D. H. Nguyen, J. Chacko, L. Henderson, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
  Proc. of 22nd Annu. Intl. Conf. on Mobile Computing and Networking (ACM MobiCom '16), 2016
- [C3] Enabling Synchronous Directional Channel Access on SDRs for Spectrum Sharing Applications
  D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
  Proc. of ACM Intl. Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Eval., and Characterization (WiNTECH '16), 2016
- [C4] Demo: Enhancing Indoor Spatial Reuse through Adaptive Antenna Beamsteering (WinCool Best Demo Award)
  D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
  Proc. of ACM Intl. Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Eval., and Characterization (WiNTECH '16), 2016
- [C5] BeamViewer: Visualization of Dynamic Antenna Radiation Patterns using Augmented Reality
  D. H. Nguyen, L. Henderson, J. Chacko, C. Sahin, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
  Proc. of IEEE Conf. on Computer Communications Workshops (INFOCOM WKSHPS '16), 2016
- [C6] Experimental Evaluation of a Reconfigurable Antenna System for Blind Interference Alignment S. Begashaw, J. Chacko, N. Gulati, D. H. Nguyen, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar

- Proc. of IEEE Wireless and Microwave Technology Conf. (WAMICON '16), 2016
- [C7] Wireless Communications Engineering and Cybersecurity Education via Augmented Reality C. Sahin, D. H. Nguyen, S. Begashaw, B. Katz, J. Chacko, L. Henderson, J. Stanford, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Frontiers in Education Conf. (FIE '16)*, 2016
- [C8] Leveraging an Agile RF Transceiver for Rapid Prototyping of Small-Cell Systems D. H. Nguyen, M. Rauhanummi, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Vehicular Technology Conf. (VTC-Fall '15)*, 2015
- [C9] Wireless Cybersecurity Education via a Software Defined Radio Laboratory C. Sahin, D. Nguyen, J. Chacko, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Frontiers in Education Conf. (FIE '15)*, 2015
- [C10] A Real-Time and Protocol-Aware Reactive Jamming Framework Built on Software-Defined Radios D. Nguyen, C. Sahin, B. Shishkin, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of ACM Workshop on Software Radio Implementation Forum (SRIF '14*), 2014
- [C11] FPGA-Based Latency-Insensitive OFDM Pipeline for Wireless Research J. Chacko, C. Sahin, D. Nguyen, D. Pfeil, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conf. (HPEC '14*), 2014
- [C12] Real-Time, Channel-Aware Reactive Jamming in 802.11 Networks
  D. Nguyen, B. Shishkin, C. Sahin, D. Dorsey, N. Kandasamy, K. Dandekar
  Proc. of 2013 Wireless @ Virginia Tech Annu. Symp. 2013
- [C13] SDC Testbed: Software Defined Communications Testbed for Wireless Radio and Optical Networking
  B. Shishkin, D. Pfeil, D. Nguyen, K. Wanuga, J. Chacko, J. Johnson, N. Kandasamy, T. P. Kurzweg, K. R. Dandekar
  Proc. of Intl. Symp. on Modeling and Optimization in Mobile, Ad Hoc, and Wireless Networks (WiOPT '11), 2011

## WORKING PAPERS (Unpublished)

[W1] LinkPursuit: An Adaptive Pursuit Learning Method to Mitigate Small-Cell Interference through Directionality D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar Submitted (unsuccessfully) to ACM MobiCom '16. Under revision, 2016

## PATENT / PATENT APPLICATIONS

- [P1] Real-Time, Channel-Aware Reactive Jamming in Wireless Networks
  B. Shishkin, D. H. Nguyen, C. Sahin, K. R. Dandekar, N. Kandasamy, D. J. Dorsey
  US Patent No. 9,531,497. Issued December 27, 2016
- [P2] Beam Visualization and STEM Education using Augmented Reality
  K. R. Dandekar, C. Sahin, L. J. Henderson, D. H. Nguyen, J. J. Chacko, X. R. Rey
  US Provisional Patent Application No. 62/403,415. Filed October 3, 2016
- [P3] An Adaptive Pursuit Learning Method to Mitigate Small-Cell Interference through Directionality D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar US Provisional Patent Application No. 62/402,671. Filed September 30, 2016

#### TECHNICAL REPORTS (Available at http://wireless.ece.drexel.edu)

- [T1] Radio Frequency Coordination at the Democratic National Convention D. H. Nguyen, M. Jacovic, I. Rasheed, K. R. Dandekar Tech. Rep. No. 1, Drexel Wireless Systems Laboratory, 2016
- [T2] Real Time Feature Detection and Threat Analysis with USRP SDR B. Shishkin, D. Nguyen, C. Sahin, C. Miller Tech. Rep. No. 2, Drexel Wireless Systems Laboratory, 2012

# Honors & Awards

2016	WinCool Best Demo, ACM WiNTECH '16 (judged by a panel from industry and academia)
2009–Present	Graduate Research Fellow, Drexel University
2008-2009	Milton Rosenberg Scholar, Drexel University (recognizing outstanding engineering students)
2009	Senior Design Competition Winner, Drexel ECE (for a real-time RFID-based product locating system)
2006-2009	Dean's Scholarship Recipient, Drexel University
2008	Inductee, Eta Kappa Nu National ECE Honor Society

# **Academic Projects**

#### NACHOS EDUCATIONAL OPERATING SYSTEM IMPLEMENTATION

Fall 2011

• Implemented in Java various features of a modern operating system: paging, virtual memory, locks and semaphores, conditional variables, and multi-threaded operations

## FAST FOURIER TRANSFORM (FFT) PERFORMANCE BENCHMARKING ON CPU AND GPU

Winter 2011

Implemented and measured runtime performance of various FFT implementation in C and CUDA

#### MULTI-THREADED MATRIX OPERATIONS USING BLAS AND LAPACK

Winter 2011

 Wrote C programs to perform LU decomposition on large matrices, then parallelized the implementations using Pthreads, OpenMP, and Cilk

#### COMPILER CONSTRUCTION FOR SPL (SIGNAL PROCESSING LANGUAGE)

Spring 2010

 Constructed a scanner, parser, and interpreter for a Lisp-style language targeted for describing signal processing kernels called SPL, using Java Lex and Yacc

#### IMPLEMENTATION OF A 5-STAGE PIPELINED CPU ON FPGA

Winter 2010

• Implemented a 5-stage pipelined CPU supporting Load/Store, R-type instructions, branching, and context switches in VHDL. Performed FPGA synthesis and verification on the Xilinx Spartan 3E board

# **Other Activities**

#### **Journal and Conference Peer-Review**

Philadelphia, PA

EXTERNAL REVIEWER

2012-Present

- Performed peer-review and provided publication recommendations for submitted manuscripts
- Journals: IEEE Trans. on Vehicular Techology, IEEE Trans. on Internet of Things
- Conferences: IEEE VTC '14 / '15, CROWNCOM '12

## National Science Foundation (NSF) Research Grant Proposals

Drexel University

**CONTRIBUTOR** 

2011-Present

- · Performed literature survey, formulated research thrusts, and assisted the Principal Investigators (PIs) in writing grant proposals
- Awarded grants to PIs: CNS-1147838 (WiFiUS 2011), CNS-1422964 (NeTS-Small 2014), CNS-1457306 (WiFiUS 2014)

## **Local Professional Meetings and Conferences**

Philadelphia, PA

STUDENT VOLUNTEER

2015-Present

Worked registration desk and monitored presentation & poster sessions at IEEE ISPASS '15, IEEE CNS '16

#### **Local Political Convention (Democratic National Convention)**

Philadelphia, PA 7/2016

RADIO FREQUENCY (RF) COORDINATION VOLUNTEER

ging, floor sweep to monitor spectrum usage, troubleshoot interference incidents. Details summarized in a technical report [T1]

· Handled the RF coordination procedure: static allocation of available spectrum to media organizations, device inspection and tag-

IEEE Student Branch

Drexel University

LOGISTICS CHAIR 2010

• Handled logistics operations in the organization: organize membership drives, book event venues, prepare refreshments and meeting materials, contact and schedule event speakers

**GSA Education. Inc.**Hanoi, Vietnam

FOUNDING MEMBER 2008

- Co-founded a professional education service company in Vietnam. Services include tutoring and college application consulting
- Led the development of the company's web portal for customer relationship management